Marcel Breuer Papers
Marcel Breuer Papers
- Furniture
  - Photographs, 105 items
    - Tables with chromium pipe legs (WB 91,92,93), [1928]; related model: 91/WB,92/WB and 93/WB; black and white photograph (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Tubular steel tea cart (B54), 1928; related model: B54; black and white photograph; "Service table with removable trays 1928"written on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Tubular steel tea cart (B54), 1928; related model: B54; black and white photograph; "Tea wagon 1928" written on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Bookshelve units, 1931; related model: 131/WB; black and white photograph; "Bücherregale 1931 (Typenmöbel)" written onback of photo (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Bookshelve units, circa 1931; related model: 131/WB; black and white photograph; "Bookshelve units 1932 (1931)" written on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Tubular metal and wood bed, 1929; black and white photograph; "[illegible] H. Wiesbaden 1929" (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Cabinet, 1921; black and white photograph; "Cabinet 1921" on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Kitchen cabinets, 1923; black and white photograph; "1923 Küchenschrank" on back of photo; photo by Eckner (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Breuer Furniture Exhibition, black and white photograph; photo of unidentified exhibition; "Milano(Gavina?)" written on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Metal lounge chair with curved front, black and white photograph; "Embru-Werke AG" stamped on back of photo. Not identified as a Breuer design. Chair very similar to Lorenz tubular steel models KS46 and 47. (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Tubular steel lounge chair by Mart Stam, 1927; black and white photograph; Weissenhof estate exhibition furniture. "Juli 1927" on back of photo (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Tubular steel lounge chair by Mart Stam, [1927]; black and white negative (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Aluminum chaise lounge with upholstery removed [Slide 90], [1934]; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tables with chromium pipe legs (WB 91, 92, 93), 1928; Slide 97; related model: 91/WB, 92/WB and 93/WB; black and white slide; "Table units 1928" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Modular Furniture System [Slide 119], [circa 1926]; black and white slide; Design for modular wall units (Box SL-3)
    - Desk, chair and lamp [Slide 240], [circa 1930]; black and white slide; interior setting (Box SL-3)
    - Desk, cabinets, tubular steel chair and table [Slide 241], [circa 1930]; black and white slide; interior setting (Box SL-3)
    - Modular furniture system ][Slide 243], [circa 1926]; black and white slide; Typen Möbel; axonometric (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel chair with cane seat (B32) [Slide 348], 1925-1928; related model: B32; black and white slide; "Tubular Chair, 1925-28" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum chair and armchair with upholstery [Slide 397], 1932-1933; related model: 307/WB and 308/WB; black and white slide; "Alum. Chairs - 1932-33" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Double cantilever aluminum chair [Slide 398], black and white slide; ALCOA chair?" BR 21" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum tables for flowers [Slide 399], [1933]; related model: 322/WB; black and white slide; Blumentische (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum lounge chairs [Slide 402], [1933]; related model: 345/WB and 346/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum chairs with plywood seat and slatted seat [Slide 403], [1933]; related model:301/WB and 305/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Double cantilever aluminum chair [Slide 404], black and white slide; ALCOA chair? (Box SL-3)
    - Short lounge chairs, aluminum and banded steel versions [Slide 405], [1933]; related model: 311/WB and 341/WB; black and white slide; "Aluminum lounge chairs" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum chairs with plywood seat and slatted seat [Slide 416], [1933]; related model:301/WB and 305/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum lounge chairs [Slide 417], [1933]; related model: 345/WB and 346/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Folding armchair [Slide 658], 1928; black and white slide; folded, back view; "Folding Chair, 1928" written on slide (Box SL-3)
    - Steel club armchair (B3) [Slide 659], [circa 1927]; related model: B3; black and white slide; Herbert Bayer designed cover for Standard Möbel catalog (Box SL-3)
    - Steel club armchair (B3) [Slide 660], [1925]; related model: B3; black and white slide; photo by Consemüller (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel and glass table (B19) [Slide 661], [1928]; elated model: B19; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel chair profiles [Slide 662], [circa 1930]; related model: B3/B35/B9/B7/B7a/B55; black and white slide; drawing (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel tea cart (B54) [Slide 664], [1928]; related model: B54; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Folding armchair [Slide 665], [1928]; black and white slide; folded, side view (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel chair with cane seat (B32) [Slide 666], [1925-1928]; related model: B32; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel tea cart (B54) [Slide 668], [1928]; related model: B54; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel chairs and conference table, tubular metal and wood bed [Slide 669], [circa 1930]; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel stools (B9) [Slide 671], [1925]; related model: B9; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Wood-slat arm chair (ti 1a) [Slide 674], [1922]; related model: ti 1a; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Side chair (ti 2) [Slide 675], [1922]; related model: ti 2; black and white slide; front and side views (Box SL-3)
    - Wood-slat arm chair (ti 1a) [Slide 676], [1922]; related model: ti 1a; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Side chair (ti 2) [Slide 677], [1922]; related model: ti 2; black and white slide; front and side views (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel and glass table (B19) [Slide 683], [1928]; related model: B19; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel stools (B9) [Slide 685], [1925]; related model: B9; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Bookshelve units [Slide 686], [1931]; related model: 131/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Tables with chromium pipe legs (WB 91, 92, 93) [Slide 689], [1928]; related model: 91/WB,92/WB and 93/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Plywood nesting chair [Slide 690], [1935]; related model: Dining Chair/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Isokon chaise lounge chair [Slide 691], [1935-1936]; related model: Long Chair/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Plywood nesting table [Slide 692], [1936]; related model: Nesting Tables/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Cut-out plywood side chair [Slide 697], [1935]; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Isokon chaise lounge chair [Slide 700], [1935-1936]; related model: Long Chair/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Plywood dining table [Slide 701], [1935]; related model: Dining Table/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Plywood side chair [Slide 702], [1935]; related model: Dining Chair/Isokon; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Children's room furniture, chairs, table and rug [Slide 705], [1922]; related model: ti 1b/ti 3a/ti 3b/ti 6; black and white slide; interior setting, rug by Benita Otte (Box SL-3)
    - Tubular steel and wood desk [Slide 707], [1927]; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
    - Aluminum chair and armchair with upholstery [Slide 745], [1933]; related model: 307/WB and 308/WB; black and white slide (Box SL-3)
- Project records
  Within each project, Drawings consists of preliminary sketches and designs, design development drawings, presentation and publication drawings, working drawings (including construction sets) and shop drawings. Project files contain correspondence with clients, engineers, contractors and manufacturers; program notes and documents; specifications documents; Financial documents (architect's fees, contractor billing and supplier invoices), consultant reports, construction bulletins, change orders, contracts, etc. Published material contains project specific articles and clippings related to subsequent presentation of completed projects. Photographs includes finished project photographs and construction photographs, slides and negatives.
  - ABRAHAM AND STRAUS, EXTERIOR, Hempstead, Long Island, NY (1950-1954). Marcel Breuer, Consulting Architect. [Commercial], (Alternate names: A & S Department Stores; Princeton Project.)
    - Drawings, 55
      - Draft elevations, design development drawings (originals); some rendered and/or with sketches in the margins; 13 (Tube 1110)
      - Rendered preliminary storefront elevations, design development drawings (originals); 7 (Tube 1110)
      - Presentation sheet with two rendered elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1110)
      - Exterior perspective rendering [photostat], presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1110)
      - Drafts of exterior perspective views of the storefront, presentation drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1110)
      - Large rendered exterior perspectives, presentation drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1110)
      - Stair details, design development drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1111)
      - Plan drafts and sketches in various stages of completion, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1111)
      - Preliminary plan of building exterior wall, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1111)
      - Preliminary and revised elevations, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1111)
      - Design details: Entrance, stone textures, showcases, etc., design development drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 1111)
      - Large scale exterior texture studies, design development drawings (originals); 5 (Tube 1111)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence: Associated architects (Sep 1950-Feb 1954), The Austin Co., Engineers and Builders (Box 78, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence: Client (Sep 1950-Nov 1953), Abraham and Straus (R.H. Brown) (Box 78, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence: Manufacturers (1950-1954), various suppliers and service providers (Box 78, Folder 3)
      - Financial records, architect invoices/payments (Box 78, Folder 4)
      - Memos (Nov 1950-Aug 1953), Project Memoranda (Box 78, Folder 5)
      - Office records, internal memoranda, miscellaneous notes (Box 78, Folder 6)
      - Promotional materials I, Abraham and Strauss Booklet (Box 78, Folder 7)
      - Promotional materials II, The Austin Co. promotional literature (Box 78, Folder 8)
      - Publicity (1950-1952), press releases, correspondence with photographers and with Architectural Record (Box 78, Folder 9)
      - Transmittals (Box 78, Folder 10)
    - Published material
      - "A & S-Nassau Store Designed...in Outlying Area " Architectural Record (Feb 1951), tear sheet; 10 pgs. (Box 78, Folder 11)
      - "New Nassau Store to Cost $2,500,000" New York Times (28 Dec 1950), photocopy; 1 pg. (Box 78, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, 6
      - A & S President viewing exhibit of scale model, model; black and white photographs; 1 (Box 78, Folder 12)
      - Building façade including entrance, finished project, exterior view; black and white photographs; 1 (Box 78, Folder 12)
      - Night view of elevation, finished project, exterior view; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 78, Folder 12)
      - Watercolor view of proposed façade, drawings, perspective rendering; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 78, Folder 12)
  - AIRPORT TERMINAL BUILDINGS, Fairbanks and Anchorage, AK (1948-1953). Marcel Breuer, Consulting Architect. [Other], (Alternate names: Anchorage Airport; Fairbanks Airport; Alaska Air Terminal.)
    - Drawings, 39
      - Construction plans for Anchorage International Express Airport (28 Sep 1948) (Thomas B. Bourne and Associates), working drawings (reproductions); 39 bound sheets (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence (May 1949-Mar 1953), bulk of the correspondence is between Breuer and representatives of Bourne Associates (Box 88, Folder 1)
      - Office records (1950-1953), architect invoices, travel documents, design specifications and miscellaneous notes (Box 88, Folder 2)
  - ALMY, BIGELOW AND WASHBURN, Salem, MA (1944-1947) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Commercial]
    - Drawings, 42
      - Rough sketches and draftsman's project sketchbook, design development drawings (originals); 30 (Box 79, Folder 11-12)
      - Details, floor layouts, interiors, working drawings (reproductions); 12 (Tube 718)
    - Project files
      - Building permits (Jan 1945-Apr 1946), correspondence/application with city of Salem authorities (Box 79, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence: Client (Aug 1944-Apr 47), Almy, Bigelow and Washburn Dept. Store (Box 79, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence: Consultants (Feb 1946-Apr 1947), Cleverdon, Varney & Pike, Structural Engineers. (Box 79, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence: Contractor (Feb 1945-Feb 1947), William H. Porter Co., Inc., general contractor. (Box 79, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence: Manufacturers (1945-46), various suppliers and service providers (Box 79, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence: Office (Jun 1946-Apr 1947), internal office correspondence with Charles Burchard, O.S. Leighton. (Box 79, Folder 6)
      - Financial records, billing documents and billing correspondence. (Box 79, Folder 7)
      - List of drawings (Box 79, Folder 8)
      - Office records, miscellaneous administrative documents, notes and contact information. (Box 79, Folder 9)
      - Program documents I (Aug 1944-Dec 1944), cost analysis, notes and computations (Box 79, Folder 10)
      - Program documents II (1944-1946), miscellaneous notes, meeting notes, computations and sketches. (Box 79, Folder 11)
      - Program documents III, Ira Rakatansky notebook (draftsman's notebook): notes, computations and sketches. (Box 79, Folder 12)
  - ALUMINUM CITY TERRACE, New Kensington, PA (1941-1944). Walter Gropius and Marcel Breuer, Architects. [Residential, Multi], (Alternate names: Defense Housing, Pittsburgh; New Kensington Project)
    - Drawings, 25
      - General site plan (Dwg. No. A-1), working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Grading plan: Northern and southern portions (Dwg. Nos. A3a, A3b), working drawings (reproductions); 3 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Plans and elevations: 2 and 3 BRM Unit (Dwg. No. A-5), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Plans and elevations: 1 BRM Unit (Dwg. No. A-8), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Plans, elevations, sections: Twin House (Dwg. No. A-9), working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Stud frame wall sections and details (Dwg. No. A-11), working drawings (reproductions); 4 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Brick veneer wall sections and details (Dwg. No. A-12), working drawings (reproductions); 3 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous exterior details, including sunshades (Dwg. No. A-13), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous exterior details, including sunshades (Dwg. No. A-13), presentation drawings (reproduction, board mounted photostat); 1 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Community and Administration Building: Plans and elevations (Dwg. No. A-16), working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Community and Administration Building: Perspective rendering, presentation drawings (reproductions); 2 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Twin House: Perspective rendering, presentation drawings (reproductions); 2 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
      - Sunshade diagrams showing critical relations of sunlight to building, presentation drawings (reproduction, negative photostat); 1 (Oversize 14, Folder 1)
    - Project files
      - Architect's statement and notes, includes notes from Breuer's post-project visit (Box 59, Folder 1)
      - Bid docs, cost estimates, etc. (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - Contract (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence: Client (FWA) (Apr 1941-Jan 1942) (Box 59, Folder 4-6)
      - Correspondence: Consultants (Box 59, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence: Contractor and manufacturers, includes product literature (Box 59, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence: General, includes post-project correspondence relating to public reception of the project (Box 59, Folder 9)
      - Drawing list (Box 60, Folder 10)
      - Financial records, Claims for Reimbursement (Nos. 1-9) and architect invoices (Box 60, Folder 11-13)
      - Miscellaneous documents, Administrative Orders and Procedures documents issued by FWA (Box 60, Folder 14)
      - Office records, office correspondence, receipts and miscellaneous (Box 60, Folder 15)
      - Publicity, quotation from Architectural Review (Box 60, Folder 16)
      - Reports, Weekly Progress Reports on Design Process submitted to FWA (Box 60, Folder 17)
      - Schedules, color scheme (Box 60, Folder 18)
      - Specifications, preliminary and miscellaneous; heating, electrical, plumbing; workmanship and material (submitted by breuer); workmanship and material (FWA issued); addendums (nos. 1-6) and revisions (Box 60, Folder 19-21)
      - Specifications, preliminary and miscellaneous; heating, electrical, plumbing; workmanship and material (submitted by breuer); workmanship and material (FWA issued); addendums (nos. 1-6) and revisions (Box 61, Folder 12-24)
    - Published material
      See also Professional Papers: Scrapbooks and clippings: Brown scrapbook (2).
      - "Aluminum City Terrace Housing " Architectural Forum (Jul 1944), tear sheet; 12 pgs (Box 61, Folder 25)
      - "Housing: The Why of Planning, " Fortune (Nov 1944), copy; 6 pgs (Box 61, Folder 25)
      - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (circa 1942-1943), 3 (Box 61, Folder 25)
    - Photographs, 7
      - Exterior view, finished project; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 61, Folder 24)
      - Site model, aerial view, black and white photograph; 1 (Box 61, Folder 24)
      - Site model, aerial view, Slide 358; model, aerial view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-1)
      - Site model, site/landscape, model; black and white photographs; photo and copy negative; 2 (Oversize 14)
      - Site model, site/landscape, model; black and white photograph; large format, board mounted, 14 x 20 in.; 1 (Oversize 14)
      - Site rendering, aerial view, drawings, aerial view; photostat; 1 (Box 61, Folder 24)
  - AMERICAN PRESS INSTITUTE CONFERENCE CENTER, Reston, VA (1971-1980). Marcel Breuer and Hamilton P. Smith, Architects. [Other], (Alternate names: API)
    This section contains material related to the original construction phase (circa 1972) and a conference center extension phase (circa 1979).
    - Drawings, 243
      - Perspective rendering, presentation drawings (originals); artist unknown; graphite on illustration board, 18 x 30 in; 1 (Map-case 116, Folder 3)
      - Presentation book (Jan 1972): Site plan, perspective rendering, architect's report, ground floor plan, upper floor plan, elevations and sections, bound volume of presentation drawings, 9 pages (Oversize 27)
      - Presentation set (Jan 1972): Site plans, ground floor plan, upper floor plan, elevations and sections (Dwg. Nos. 1-4), presentation drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1383)
      - Presentation set / book negatives (Jan 1972), presentation drawings (reproductions); large format film negatives for presentation book and presentation set; 11 (Tube 1383)
      - Furniture plan: Ground and upper floors, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1383)
      - Ground and upper floor plans, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1383)
      - Furnishing layout: Ground and upper floors, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1383)
      - Construction set (26 May 1972): Architectural (A1-A23), working drawings (originals); marked "issued for bid"; 26 (Tube 1384)
      - Construction set (1 Jun 1972): Structural (S1-S3), working drawings (originals); marked "issued for bid"; 3 (Tube 1384)
      - Construction set (1 Jun 1972): Mechanical (ME1-ME7), electrical (E1-E4), working drawings (reproductions); marked "issued for bidding"; 12 (Tube 1384)
      - Miscellaneous revisions (Feb 1973-Mar 1974): Dwg. Nos. A4-A6, A17, A20, A22-A23, working drawings (reproductions); 5 (Tube 1384)
      - Site work, surveys and topographic maps (1972-1978), design development drawings (reproductions); some annotated prints; includes original phase and extension phase; 34 (Tube 1381)
      - Design development, SK drawings and miscellaneous detail and furniture drawings (1972-1980), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes conference table drawings (circa 1980), furniture built-ins and floor plan studies; 32 (Tube 1382)
      - General study (Nov 1978): Dwg. Nos. D1-D10, design development drawings (reproductions); annotated prints; 14 (Tube 1382)
      - Audio-visual facilities plan (28 Dec 1978) (Habert Wilke), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1382)
      - Carpet and drapery (15 Jan 1980): Dwg. Nos. CD1-CD2, working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1382)
      - Furniture layout (15 Jan 1980): Dwg. Nos. LA1-LA2, working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1382)
      - Wall finishes (15 Jan 1980): Dwg. Nos. FI1-FI2, working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1382)
      - Credit wall (6 Jun 1980), working drawings (reproductions); 3 copies, 1 with revisions (Tube 1382)
      - Lighting (26 Jan 1979): Dwg. Nos. L2-L3, working drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1382)
      - Ground floor power plan (14 Sep 1979), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1382)
      - Square footage, ground and upper floors, working drawings (reproductions); annotated prints; 2 (Tube 1382)
      - Furniture SK drawings (Nov-Dec 1979): Dwg. Nos. SK1-SK13 and miscellaneous sheets, working drawings (reproductions); annotated prints; 21 (Tube 1382)
      - Conference Center Expansion. Construction set (15 Feb 1979): Architectural (A0-A18), structural (S1-S4), plus 2 duplicates and S4-S5 reference drawings from 1972 Construction set, working drawings (originals); 27 (Tube 1385)
      - Conference Center Expansion. Construction set (15 Feb 1979): Architectural (A0-A17), structural (S1-S3); mechanical (M3-M4), working drawings (reproductions); some with annotations; 23 (Tube 1386)
    - Project files
      - Bid documents (Box 141, Folder 1)
      - Building codes (Box 141, Folder 2)
      - Change orders (Nos. 1-30) (Box 141, Folder 3-4)
      - Closing documents (Box 141, Folder 5)
      - Contracts and contract negotiation (Box 141, Folder 6-7)
      - Correspondence: Client (1971-1977), American Press Institute (Box 141, Folder 8-10)
      - Correspondence: Consultant acoustic engineer (Box 141, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, engineers, concrete inspection (Box 141, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, food service (Box 141, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, lighting (Box 141, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, material research (Box 142, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, mechanical and electrical engineers (Box 142, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, structural engineer (Box 142, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, surveyor (Box 142, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence: Consultant, Edward Zekala, specifications writer (Box 142, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence: Contractor (1972-1975), Sharpe and Hamaker, Inc., general contractor (Box 142, Folder 6-8)
      - Correspondence: Gulf Reston (Box 143, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence: Office (Box 143, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence: Miscellaneous (Box 143, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence: Municipal agencies (Box 143, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence: Supplier, carpeting (Box 143, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence: Supplier, furnishings (Box 143, Folder 6)